<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>credit scoring | Rodrigo Lira</title>
    <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/tag/credit-scoring/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://rodrigoclira.github.io/tag/credit-scoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>credit scoring</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>pt</language><copyright>Rodrigo Lira · 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 23:57:14 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/images/icon_huf2b89bb3aeddaf27bedd36282c847631_693_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>credit scoring</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/tag/credit-scoring/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publicação no Symposium on Knowledge Discovery, Mining and Learning (KDMiLe 2020)</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/post/kdmile2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 23:57:14 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/post/kdmile2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;O artigo &amp;ldquo;Impact of Unusual Features in Credit Scoring Problem&amp;rdquo; foi aceito no 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.sbc.org.br/bracis2020/kdmile.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Symposium on Knowledge Discovery, Mining and Learning (KDMiLe)&lt;/a&gt;. O trabalho foi fruto do projeto da disciplina de Mineração de Dados do PPGEC/Ecomp. Mais informações sobre o artigo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autores: L. F. Vercosa, &lt;strong&gt;R. Lira&lt;/strong&gt;, R. Monteiro, K. Silva, J. Magalhaes, A. Maciel, B. Leite, C. Bastos-Filho&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:
&amp;ldquo;Standard features used for Credit Scoring includes mainly registration and financial data from customers. However, exploring new features is of great interest for financial companies, since slight improvements in the person score directly impact the company revenue. In this work, we categorize features from open credit scoring datasets and compare them with the features found in a real company dataset. The company dataset contains unusual feature groups such as historical, geolocation, web behavior, and demographic data. We performed bivariate tests using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov metric and features to assess the performance of the particular feature groups. We also generated a score of good payer by using AdaBoost, Multilayer Perceptron, and XGBoost algorithms. Then, we analyzed the results with different metrics and compared them with the real company results. Our main finding was that these features added a small improvement to current datasets. We also identified the most promising feature groups and noticed that the tuned XGBoost performed better than the company solution in three out of four deployed metrics.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
