<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>swarm intelligence | Rodrigo Lira</title>
    <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/tag/swarm-intelligence/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://rodrigoclira.github.io/tag/swarm-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>swarm intelligence</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>pt</language><copyright>Rodrigo Lira · 2026</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:10:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/media/icon_huf2b89bb3aeddaf27bedd36282c847631_693_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>swarm intelligence</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/tag/swarm-intelligence/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swarm Dynamics Frameworks</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/post/2026/swarm-dynamics-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:10:00 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/post/2026/swarm-dynamics-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;interaction-networks&#34;&gt;Interaction Networks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oliveira et. al. [1] proposed a framework named Interaction Networks (IN) that captures the social interactions between individuals in Swarm Intelligence metaheuristics. This network-based approach provides a meso-level perspective between the micro-level rules followed by individual agents and the macro-level performance of the metaheuristic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an Interaction Network, nodes represent agents in the swarm, while the edges represent the interactions among them. The network I(t) describes the interactions at time &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;, with edges I$_{ij}$ indicating the extent to which agent &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; influences the movement of agent &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, Interaction Network captures actual information exchanges that occur during the optimisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;search-trajectory-networks&#34;&gt;Search Trajectory Networks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced by Ochoa et. al. [2], Search Trajectory Networks (STNs) provide a tool for analysing and visualising the behaviour of algorithms during optimisation. STNs transform the complex search trajectories of algorithms into network representations that can be quantitatively analysed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an STNs, nodes represent locations in the search space, and edges represent transitions between these locations. A location is defined as a subset of the search space resulting from partitioning, and each search trajectory is a sequence of locations visited by representative solutions. Unlike Interaction Networks that focus on agent relationships, STNs focus on how algorithms traverse the search space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STNs can be constructed for any metaheuristic algorithm, whether population-based or single-solution based. Moreover, STNs from different algorithms can be merged into a single model. In the STN framework, each node represents a location in the search space containing at least one representative solution from the algorithm&amp;rsquo;s trajectory [3]. For continuous optimisation problems, these locations are typically defined by partitioning the search space into hypercubes of a predetermined size, effectively mapping the high-dimensional solution space onto a more manageable network representation while preserving the essential characteristics of the search behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement-frequency-and-population-turnover&#34;&gt;Improvement Frequency and Population Turnover&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hayward and Engelbrecht [4] introduced two metrics to characterise swarm dynamics in metaheuristics: Improvement Frequency and Population Turnover. These two metrics provide simple yet effective ways to visualise and analyse the fitness behaviour of swarm-based metaheuristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improvement Frequency tracks when agents improve their fitness during the search process. It reveals patterns of ``freshness&#39;&#39; in the population, with coloured clusters indicating active improvement periods and uncoloured spaces showing information staleness. The temporal patterns in these improvements help identify how information propagates through the swarm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population Turnover measures the breadth of good information by tracking how many agents improved their fitness at each iteration. It helps identify distinct behaviour stages in the algorithm&amp;rsquo;s execution,  revealing when exploration or exploitation dominates the search process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these metrics provide insights into how information spreads and influences the swarm over time. When visualised, they create distinctive patterns that characterise different metaheuristics and their behaviour on specific problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;referências&#34;&gt;Referências&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Oliveira, M., Bastos-Filho, C.J.A., Menezes, R.: Using network science to assess particle swarm optimizers. Social Network Analysis and Mining 5(1), 3 (Jan 2015). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s13278-015-0245-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s13278-015-0245-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Ochoa, G., Malan, K.M., Blum, C.: Search trajectory networks: A tool for analysing and visualising the behaviour of metaheuristics. Applied Soft Computing 109, 107492 (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.asoc.2021.107492&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.asoc.2021.107492&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Narvaez-Teran, V., Ochoa, G., Rodriguez-Tello, E.: Search trajectory networks applied to the cyclic bandwidth sum problem. IEEE Access 9, 151266–151277 (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ACCESS.2021.3126015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/ACCESS.2021.3126015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] heuristic search behaviour characteristics. In: Proceedings of the Companion Conference on Genetic and Evolutionary Computation. p. 1562–1569. GECCO ’23 Companion, Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA (2023). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1145/3583133.3596338&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1145/3583133.3596338&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multidimensional Analysis of Swarm Dynamics in a Reinforcement Learning based Metaheuristic</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/a-multidimensional-analysis-of-swarm-dynamics-in-a-reinforcement-learning-based-metaheuristic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/a-multidimensional-analysis-of-swarm-dynamics-in-a-reinforcement-learning-based-metaheuristic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;responsive-wrap&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vTw8Soalhf6olSm4LvMuehON08QoeS-EkvCUGPaOIEwZ4qD7inBPjXtcmOABnP_uUknyMl3TCwVLahi/pubembed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;569&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Social Dynamics in a Reinforcement Learning-based Metaheuristic - A study using Improvement Frequency and Population Turnover</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/exploring-social-dynamics-in-a-reinforcement-learning-based-metaheuristic-a-study-using-improvement-frequency-and-population-turnover/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/exploring-social-dynamics-in-a-reinforcement-learning-based-metaheuristic-a-study-using-improvement-frequency-and-population-turnover/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;responsive-wrap&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vT_cTBglurlzIJaP7_OeSmOFE_iR8FeDP_a-jUe5jALFGlF0A4uXTabRO7P9RVuCb3G8sYJycMwSR4T/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;569&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Reinforcement Learning to Combine Multiple Swarm-based Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/applying-reinforcement-learning-to-combine-multiple-swarm-based-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/applying-reinforcement-learning-to-combine-multiple-swarm-based-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;responsive-wrap&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vSbE4VhbB5g93wNH0O3sH2z4U0AzwgXBQcgEPX8o_UlcvEqp1Pf-F25F18PyTsObzfXjsS2_wYEF0wi/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;569&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Reinforcement Learning for Multiple Functions in Swarm Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/applying-reinforcement-learning-for-multiple-functions-in-swarm-intelligence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/talk/applying-reinforcement-learning-for-multiple-functions-in-swarm-intelligence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;responsive-wrap&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vTpPPjfMMDMwKfvTdcdDvUla1c0hghKYRYbZb46VSu_onSE6OeoRt9U7eENOs06CLwll5TwNrUf4GuF/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;569&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inteligência de enxames com aprendizado de máquina por reforço para resolução de problemas de otimização</title>
      <link>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/project/rl-mh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodrigoclira.github.io/project/rl-mh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inteligência de enxames é uma subárea de computação inteligente que compreende abordagens que se inspiram no comportamento inteligente emergente da interação entre seres vivos para resolução de problemas complexos. Ao longo das últimas três décadas, muitas foram as propostas que surgiram na área, as quais são baseadas nas mais diversas metáforas. Uma característica em comum a essas propostas é que os agentes costumam seguir em todo o processo de resolução do problema a inspiração utilizada na sua concepção. Sabendo-se que existem diversos problemas de otimização e que mesmo em um único problema existem fases que precisam de diferentes comportamentos, seguir um conjunto de operadores bem definido por um algoritmo é um fator limitante. Por esse motivo, este projeto visa desenvolver uma meta-heurística adaptativa para resolução de problemas de otimização que consiga se auto-organizar no exame (ou sub-enxames) mais promissor de acordo com informações obtidas &lt;em&gt;on-line&lt;/em&gt; na execução.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--









  





&lt;video autoplay loop  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://rodrigoclira.github.io/project/rl-mh/passaros-alpha.webm&#34; type=&#34;video/webm&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
